A Guide to the John V. Becker Papers, 1936-1980, n.d.
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
John V. Becker Papers
1936-1980, n.d.
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Becker, John Vernon, 1913-
Ms1990-052
5.4 Cubic Feet 4 boxes
Papers include correspondence, notes, memoranda and other materials related to NACA and NASA programs with which Becker was associated, including the X-1, X-15, X-20 (or Dyna-Soar) programs; research files for The High-Speed Frontier; transcripts of oral history interviews; and copies of publications and lectures by Becker, created between 1936 and 1980.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for use.
Acquisition Information
The John V. Becker Papers were donated to Special Collections prior to 1990.
Biographical Note
John V. Becker was born in Albany, New York, in 1913. He graduated from NYU in 1935 with a degree in mechanical engineering and an MS in 1936. He began working at National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics (NACA) in the Langley Memorial Aeronautical Laboratory later that year. During his career, he served as. Head of the 16-ft. Wind Tunnel Branch (1943-1947), chief of the Compressibility Research Division (1947-1957), and chief of the Aero-Physics Research Division (1958-1974) at NACA and NASA-Langley. He was a specialist in hypersonic and reentry aerodynamics and a pioneer in the development of hypersonic research aircraft, including the X-15. Becker retired from NASA in 1974. He was elected a fellow of the American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics. In 1980, he authored The High-Speed Frontier: Case Histories of Four NACA Programs, 1920-1950 (Washington, DC: NASA, 1980).
A longer biography of Becker is availalbe on the NASA website: https://www.nasa.gov/langley/hall-of-honor/john-v-becker.
Scope and Content
The John V. Becker Papers contain correspondence, notes, memoranda and other materials related to NACA and NASA programs with which Becker was associated, including the X-1, X-15, X-20 (or Dyna-Soar) programs, research files for The High-Speed Frontier and other writings, transcripts of oral history interviews, and copies of publications and lectures by Becker. The majority of materials were created between 1936 and 1980, with the bulk dated between 1946 and 1976. There are also undated materials, but based on their content, they date to the same active time period of Becker's career.
Arrangement
The John V. Becker Papers are in their original order. Since this order grouped like materials together, series were added to help navigate the collection. Series I: Biographical Information and Correspondence, 1936-1976, n.d., contains resumes, interviews with Becker, correspondence, and materials about his retirement. Series II: Writings and Authored Studies, 1970-1980, n.d., includes books, reports, and studies written by Becker and reviews about those works. In addition, this series has writings by colleagues on which Becker commented. Series III: Talks and Presentations, 1946-1976, consists of talks and presentations given by Becker between 1946 and 1976. These include presentations given to the public (at conferences or invited events), as well as presentation given in the context of his job (for the military, NASA, and corporate partners). Series IV: Research and Meeting Files, 1954-1974, n.d., contains research and subject files on various projects from Becker's career including, but not limited to, wind tunnels, hypersonic and supersonic flight, the X-15 (and precursors and successors), Dyna-Soar, and active cooling programs. In additions, this contains series contains notes from meetings with sueprvisors, project partners, committees. This series may also have correspondence not located in Series I.
Archives of American Aerospace Exploration (AAAE); Aerospace engineers; Science and Technology
- Series I: Biographical Information and Correspondence, 1936-1976, n.d.
  - Biographical data, resumes, etc. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Interviews: May 27, 1973-Walt Bonney; February 10, 1976-Gene Emme (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - List of Publications (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 4a-4b)
  - Correspondence, Appointments to advisory groups, committees, 1936-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4c)
  - Correspondence, Banquets & Awards (Box 1, Folder 4d)
  - Retirement, 1975-1990 (Box 1, Folder 4e)
- Series II: Writings and Authored Studies, 1970-1980, n.d.
  - Roland's NACA History-JVB Comments (Box 1, Folder 5a)
  - Hansen's Langley History (Box 1, Folder 5b)
  - Book Review-Hallion's Dryden History (Box 1, Folder 5c)
  - HRE Hindsight Study-Pre-HRE Scram jet res., aerospace plane (Box 1, Folder 6a)
  - HRE Hindsight Study-Contract, Report correspondence (Box 1, Folder 6b)
  - HRE Hindsight Study-Coord. National Programs (Box 1, Folder 6c)
  - HRE Hindsight Study-Final Report (Box 1, Folder 6d)
  - HRE Hindsight Study-Comments (Box 1, Folder 6e)
  - DuPont Engine Study, 1970-1977 (Box 1, Folder 6f)
  - The High Speed Frontier-Correspondence, proposals, contract (Box 1, Folder 7a)
  - The High Speed Frontier-Interviews (Box 1, Folder 7b)
  - The High Speed Frontier-Sample taped interviews (Box 1, Folder 7c)
  - Unused writings for SP445 (Box 1, Folder 7d)
  - The High Speed Frontier (NASA SP445)-2 reviews, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 7e)
  - Reviews and comments on The High Speed Frontier (Box 1, Folder 7f)
  - The Development of Winged Reentry Vehicles (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series III: Talks and Presentations, 1946-1976
  - Aviation Writers Association talk, 2/7/1946 (Box 1, Folder 9a)
  - "Problems in Newer Fields of Fluid Mechanics," December 29, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 9b)
  - "States of 2-Dimension Transonic Research," June 1950 (Box 1, Folder 9c)
  - Chairman's remarks, October 2-3, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 9d)
  - "Scale Effects at Supersonic Speeds," September 1953 (Box 1, Folder 9e)
  - "Supersonic Heat Transfer on Flared Bodies," January 19, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 9f)
  - "Future Aircraft," March 28, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 9g)
  - "Hypersonic Gliders," May 1, 1957; "The Coolant Requirements of Hypersonic Gliders," November 4, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 9h)
  - "Winged Configurations for Manned Satellites," March 1958 (Box 1, Folder 9i)
  - "Reentry" lecture, November 26, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 9j)
  - "Comparisons of X-15, Mercury and Dyna-soar," February 10, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 9k)
  - "Comparative Studies of Reentry Vehicles," April 7, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 9l)
  - "Manned Hypersonic Vehicles," 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 9m)
  - "State of the Art 1959 Manned Reentry Vehicles," July 28, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 9n)
  - "Reentry" lecture, September 9, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 9o)
  - "Supersatellite Reentry," December 2-4, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 9p)
  - "Reentry R & D," 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 9q)
  - "Trajectory Control-Reentry at Escape Speed," June 21, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 9r)
  - "Reentry from Lunar Missionsm" August 5, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 9s)
  - "Reentry from Lunar Missions," September 8, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 9t)
  - RESA lecture, October 17, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Facilities for Hypersonic Research," September 14, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Reentry from Deep Space Missions," October 17, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - OART studies, June 25, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Studies of High L/D Hypersonic Config ICAS IV," August 8, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "Research on Hypersonic Aircraft," January 14, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Fluid Mechanics Problems of Hypersonic Aircraft," August 28-31, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "The Evolution of Lifting Body R.V.s," December 1967 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "A Critical Look at the R & D of Hypersonic Aircraft," October 24, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "Research and Development for Long Range Supersonic Aircraft," November 1, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 10a)
  - "X-15 in Retrospect," December 4-5, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 10b)
  - "Research and Project Management," March 13, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Hypersonic Technology Briefings for G. Low, June 8, 1970, and D. Nicks, April 23, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - ICAS VII, September 1970 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Aeronautical Research Beyond Mach 3, July 15, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - NASA/OAST Hypersonic Technology Programs, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "Actively Cooled Hypersonic Aircraft," May 18, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - "Transport A/C Opportunities Beyond the M-2.7 SSt," July 27, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - "Hypersonic Technology", March 19, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - "Reflections on Hypersonics," December 5, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Series IV: Research and Meeting Files, 1954-1974, n.d.
  - Langley Wind Tunnel Development (Box 2, Folder 20a)
  - 4-ft Supersonic Tunnel (Box 2, Folder 20b)
  - 60,000 hp Compressor for 4ft Supersonic Tunnel-Design, manufacture, test photos (Box 2, Folder 20c)
  - Analysis of Ram-Jet-powered wind tunnel (Box 2, Folder 20d)
  - Use of gases other than air in hypersonic tunnels (Box 2, Folder 20e)
  - Alternates to slotted throats for transonic testing in 16 ft tunnel (Box 2, Folder 20f)
  - Isentropic Compressor, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 20g)
  - 11-inch Hypersonic Wind Tunnel-conception, progress reports, early research, initial design (Box 2, Folder 20h)
  - 11-inch Hypersonic Wind Tunnel-photos (Box 2, Folder 20i)
  - 11-inch Hypersonic Wind Tunnel-Tests, tech reports, transfer to Virginia Tech (Box 2, Folder 20j)
  - X-1 research airplane (conceptual predecessor to X-15) (Box 2, Folder 21a)
  - Langley pre-X-15 study of 1954 (Box 2, Folder 21b-c)
  - Bell aircraft and Douglas visitors, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 21c)
  - Project 1226 (X-15), 1955 (Box 2, Folder 21d)
  - X-15 Evaluation of contract proposals, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 21e)
  - X-15 Design phase (samples) (Box 2, Folder 21f)
  - X-15, Advances in technology (Box 2, Folder 21g)
  - X-15 Follow-on program, termination (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - X-15 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - X-15 History, retrospective assessment (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - X-15 Sample correspondence (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Hypersonic Research Airplane Study, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 5a)
  - Round III meetings, October 16-18, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 5b)
  - "Minimum Manned Satellite," WADC Briefings, January 30-31, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Dyna-soar, X-20 Concept, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 7a)
  - X-20 Controls (Box 3, Folder 7b)
  - Dyna-soar correspondence, 1959-1962 (Box 3, Folder 7c)
  - Korycircki Log of Key Dyna-soar Office Activies, 1957-1962 (Box 3, Folder 7d)
  - RVX-2, Proposed flight tests to validate Dyna-soar heating and aerodynamics (Box 3, Folder 7e)
  - Dyna-soar related ASAF's Asset Project (Box 3, Folder 7f)
  - Dyna-soar Reviews (Box 3, Folder 7g)
  - Dyna-soar Briefings, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 7h)
  - Dyna-soar Final Crises and Demise, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 7i)
  - Dyna-soar Problem Areas remaining for R&D (Box 3, Folder 7j)
  - 1968 Hypersonic Research Airplane study (Box 3, Folder 8a)
  - 1972 Hypersonic Research Airplane reviews (Box 3, Folder 8b)
  - Hypersonic Research Airplane industry field trip, June 1972 (Box 3, Folder 8c)
  - "MARV" proposal, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 8d)
  - X-24C approach to a hypersonic research airplane, 1974, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 8e)
  - NASA/USAF position paper advocating a hypersonic research airplane, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 8f)
  - Lunar Mission Steering Group (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Reentry Research Steering Committee, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 10a)
  - Reentry flight tests, January 7, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 10b)
  - Reentry Flight Program Presentations, November 7, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - RVX-2 Proposal, April 1, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Reentry Flight Tests-supercircular speed, project fire (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Airbreathing Launch Vehicle Studies (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Supersonic Transport R&D; Hypersonic Transport R&D; Crituque of OART Program (Box 4, Folder 5a)
  - OART Management Council Reviews Hypersonic Technology Program, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 5b)
  - Joint NASA/USAF Hypersonic Program, November 9, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 6a)
  - USAF/NASA Scramjet Programs Reviews, 1965-1967 (Box 4, Folder 6b)
  - USAF/NASA Review of AEDC Triplet Facility, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 6c)
  - AACB-DOD/NASA Joint Study, Hypersonic Technlogy, September 1972 (Box 4, Folder 6d)
  - DOD/NASA Joint Reviews, Supersonic/Hypersonic Programs, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 6e)
  - Active Cooling Aircraft Proposal-History and initial publications, 1966-1974 (Box 4, Folder 7a)
  - Symposium on Active Cooling Airframes, November 17, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 7b)
  - Active Cooling Structures Program, November 21, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 7c)
  - Active Cooling Inter-directional Group, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 7d)
  - Active Cooling Program and Reviews, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 7e)
  - Reorganizations, 1969-1974 (Box 4, Folder 8a)
  - Exchanges with director (Box 4, Folder 8b)
  - Airlie House Retreats, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 8c)
  - Williamsburg Retreat, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 8d)
  - LRC Aircraft Design Steering Committee-Critiques of Aeronautics Program (Box 4, Folder 8e)
  - Director's Reviews Aero-physics Division, 1968; Hypersonic Division, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 8f)
  - Committee on Studies & Analogues, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 8g)
  - Technical Report Survey, Theorhetical vs. Experimental (Box 4, Folder 8h)